have you ever been backpacking and lost  and really hungry where every plant  looks delicious you'll definitely want  to stick around  [Music]  welcome back to outdoor skills made easy  if you're in a serious survival  situation pretty soon every plant starts  to look delicious and you want to make  sure that you know which ones are edible  and which ones are not a great thing to  do when you're out hiking is take a  plant identification guide so that you  can  hike along see something that you're not  familiar with and then check it out  there are also some great apps out there  that you can download but a lot of times  when we're out in the woods  we don't have the cell service to be  able to use those apps so a plant guide  in the book is a handy thing  here for example we've got  maybe a misunderstood little plant  some people might mistake that for  a stinging nettle or poison ivy now the  great thing about this it's easy to  identify  we've got a nice square stem here  and then as you smell it  you can actually smell the minty smell  if it's got an almond smell if it's a  bark or a stem that smells like almond  that's not good also as you break the  stem  if it's milky  that's an indication that your plant  might be poisonous there are some steps  that you want to progress through to see  if a plant really is edible  the first thing is to  break each plant that you're thinking  about eating into the different parts  the root  or the the leaves  the stem  the head or the flower and so we just  picked a dandelion that's universally  recognized  and we'll just pick one of the leaves  and let's say that we don't know that  the leaves might be edible which i've  eaten a lot of dandelion  but you can take the leaf and first  we're going to rub it on the inside of  our wrist or maybe up here on the inside  of the elbow  and just see if you get a rash or some  kind of a stinging reaction  that would be the first test the next  best thing to do is to cook the part of  the plant that you want to eat  some parts of plants are not edible raw  but they are when they're cooked  so cook the part that you want  and then  it's time for the lip test so you're  going to rub that on your lip  and wait about 15 minutes to see if you  get any type of a reaction a burning or  a rash or stinging  and if that's okay  then you want to go ahead and take a  little bite  and eat it and then you're going to have  to wait a few hours which is really hard  if you're hungry  but if after a few hours you're not  feeling the ill effects of anything  you're probably safe to go ahead and eat  to enhance your enjoyment while you're  out hiking we really do encourage you to  get a plant identification guide and  learn about the plants around you before  you get lost it's always a good idea we  hope that this has been informative for  you and we hope that you'll join us  again at osme tv  [Music]  you